亲爱的  那是什么
Honey, what is that?
找到了
Found it.
爸  扔了吧  怪恶心的
Dad, you should toss that. It's getting kind of gross.
扔掉饼干天使  才不呢
Toss cookie angel? No way.
这是你一年级时做了送我的
You made this for me in first grade...
用你那胖乎乎的小手
With your chubby little hands.
亲爱的  麻烦再帮我
Darling, could you pick me up
拿一瓶烈酒做圣诞甜酒
an extra bottle of aquavit for our glogg?
再来瓶烈酒
An extra bottle of 100 proof?
你不是在篡改咱们神圣的圣诞甜酒配方吧
You're not tampering with our sacred holiday recipe?
不是  我只是多做一大份
No, no, no. I'm just gonna make an extra-large batch
在平安夜唱颂歌时带上
to take with me christmas eve caroling.
当然  是在我们吃完平安夜晚餐后
Oh, it'll be after our christmas dinner.
你不介意吧
You don't mind, do you?
但那是平安夜啊  是我们拆礼物的时候
But it's christmas eve. That's when we open the gifts.
圣诞节早上拆也可以啊
Well, maybe we can open them in the morning.
早上  早上是长袜惊喜的时间
In the morning? Mornings are for stockings.
我想
Well, I-I think--
我想阿丽克西斯是想说
I think what Alexis is trying to say
她也另有安排了
is that she has other plans, too.
只是和朋友们一起  只是...
Just with a couple of friends. It's...
什么朋友  什么安排
What friends? What plans?
那我们的家族传统怎么办
What is happening to our family tradition?
爸  我觉得你的反应有点夸张
Dad, I think you're kind of overreacting.
我没有反应夸张
I am not overreacting.
一年就这么一天
It's--its one night out of the year.
要求按传统来很过分吗
Is it too much to ask to stick to the program?
也许你的传统应该变通下
Maybe your program should evolve a little.
有变通啊  我不是邀请了你吗
It is evolving. I invited you, didn't I?
你会来吧
You are still coming, right?
来  只要我不用工作
Uh, ye--I mean, if I don't have to work.
但听着  不送礼物  知道吗
But look, okay. No presents, remember?
我们说好的  只是
We promised. It's just--
这是我们在一起后第一个圣诞  有点压力
It's a little too stressful this first year.
不送礼物
No presents.
我这人很灵活的
I'm flexible.
圣诞节的有些精髓是经过时间考验的
There are certain aspects to this that are time honored--
那种心情
The...the heart..
圣诞节带来的那种心跳加速的感觉
The beating heart behind the christmas holidays.
现在连圣诞老人都挂了吗
And now Santa is dead?
有没有搞错啊
When will it end?
不想打破你的美梦  卡塞尔
Hate to break it to you, Castle,
不过圣诞老人是不存在的
but there is no Santa.
不再存在了
Well, not anymore.
你得承认  那一脸胡须加大肚腩
You gotta admit, with that beard and that belly,
这位圣诞老人还挺货真价实的
he looks like the real deal.
如果说"货真价实"是指
If by "The real deal," you mean
一位穿着红衣的体重超标人士
an overweight man in a red suit
希望他带着身份证
who was hopefully carrying I.D.
带着呢
Yeah.
还有许多拐杖糖的包装纸
Along with lots of candy canes wrappers.
不过我觉得他的身份证
Though I don't think that I.D. of his
对你没什么帮助
is gonna do you much good.
姓名"圣诞老人"  地址"北极"
"Kris Kringle." Address...north pole?
真可爱
That's cute.
也许他真的是圣诞老人
Maybe he's the real Santa,
就像电影《34街的奇迹》
like in "Miracle on 34th street."
是啊  只可惜不是快乐大结局
Yeah, but with no happy ending.
这位圣诞老人在9点半左右从天上掉下来
This Santa fell out of the sky around 9:30.
从飞机上吗
From an aircraft?
有可能  但不是民航
Maybe, but it wasn't a commercial plane,
这点可以肯定
I can tell you that.
如果从高空跌落
With a fall from high altitude,
眼睛和面部会出现冻伤
we'd see severe frostbite on his eyes and his face.
我问过那家人了
Hey. So I just talked with the family.
他们没看到也没听到有飞机飞过
They didn't see or hear any planes overhead.
这样说不通
That doesn't make any sense.
他肯定是从哪里掉下来的
He had to have fallen from somewhere.
打扰下
I'm sorry.
这么明显大家没看到吗
Are we overlooking the obvious here?
他遭遇了气流  从雪橇上滑落
He hit some turbulence, slipped out of his sleigh,
就此丧命
and fell to his doom.
圣诞老人  死在了那里
Santa... lying there dead.
禁不住问自己  我们活在怎样的世界啊
You gotta ask yourself, what kind of world do we live in?
活在不存在圣诞老人的世界
A world in which there is no Santa
而且人不会凭空从空中掉落
and people don't fall out of nowhere.
麻烦你去查下飞行管制中心
Can you check with air traffic control
看看这地区有什么飞机经过
and find out what flights were in the area?
好的  去他的圣诞节
Sure. Bah humbug.
是摔死的吗
So was the fall cause of death?
看起来是的  但只有送回
It looks like it, but I won't know for sure
验尸房才知道具体情况
until I get him back to the morgue.
无论是不是圣诞老人  他都很投入
Well, Santa or no, he sure is committed.
你说他的钱包是空的
And you're saying there's nothing in his wallet
-没东西鉴定他的身份  -是的
- that indicates a break in character? - Nope.
除了这双靴子
Except for these boots.
肯定不是北极的
They are definitely not from the north pole.
这是皇后区一家皮鞋店定做的
They're custom made from a leather shop in Queens.
我曾经定做过摩托车靴子
Got a pair of motorcycle boots there.
希望他们有记录可以鉴定他的身份
Hopefully they'll have a record of who this man is.
飞行管制中心回信了
Hey. So I heard from air traffic control
但结果你肯定不爱听
but you're not gonna like the news.
被害人落地时  中心没有记录
They have no record of anyone flying over the park
有飞机飞过公园
during the time our guy hit the ground.
这怎么可能呢
How is that even possible?
圣诞老人的雪橇进入了隐形模式
Santa had his sleigh in stealth mode.
不  我是说911之后  怎么可能
No. I mean, after 9/11, how is it possible
有人能飞过曼哈顿
that someone can just fly over Manhattan?
观光直升机一直在飞
Sightseeing choppers do it all the time.
有一次  我在午夜绕着
There was this one time, I took a midnight loop
自由女神像兜了一圈  同行的是一位拉丁
around the statue of liberty with this latin...
出版商
Publisher.
他说的对
No, he's right.
曼哈顿飞行管制中心
There's Manhattan flight corridor
不要求上报飞行
which doesn't require you to radio in
只要高度在1300英尺以下就可以
if you stay under 1,300 feet.
我婆婆是持牌飞行员
My mother-in-law is a licensed pilot,
她一再提醒我这点
as she keeps reminding me.
很大程度上让我感觉自己很挫
Part of a larger effort to make me feel inferior.
抱歉  刚才这句我有说出声吗
I'm sorry. Did I just say that out loud?
听起来她和你住一起  警监
Sounds like she's staying with you, Captain?
很快会有一天  你的岳父母也会来
One day soon, your in-laws will visit, too,
他们来了后
And when they do,
住酒店才是明智的
think hotel.
上帝啊  我讨厌过节
Lord, I hate the holidays.
她和圣诞怪杰又有了一处共同特质
Yet another quality she has in common with the Grinch.
如果不知道圣诞老人是从哪里落下的
So if we don't know where our Santa fell from,
至少知道他是谁了吧
do we at least know who he is?
希望很快知道
Well, hopefully we will soon.
警员已经通知了皇后区靴店的老板
Unis rousted the owner of that boot store in Queens.
让他开了店查发票记录
They're getting him to open up the shop and check his invoices.
蕾妮那边有消息
Lanie's got something for us.
-靴子有消息了就告诉我  -好的
- Can you keep us posted on the boots? - Yeah.
这案子让你很难受啊  兄弟
You're taking this one kinda hard, bro.
他是纯真童年的象征
He's a symbol of childhood innocence.
让我琢磨这对未来意味着什么
Makes me wonder what this means for the future.
意味着少了一个打扮成圣诞老人的人
It means there's gonna be one less guy dressed up as Santa.
嘿  平安夜快到了
Hey, so, uh, we're coming up on christmas eve.
今年继续照传统吗
We gonna keep the tradition going?
兄弟两个  六罐啤酒  对着电视彻夜狂欢
You, me, a six-pack, madden on the big screen?
知道吗
You know, I, um...
我想珍妮今年有了其它的安排
I think Jenny has other plans this year.
好吧
Yeah.
还记得你问是不是摔死的吗
Remember how you asked if that fall is what killed him?
不是的
Well, it wasn't.
从背部取出来的
I pulled this out of his back.
这是点38
And that is a .38.
你依然觉得他是从雪橇上掉下来的吗  卡塞尔
Do you still think he fell off his sleigh, Castle?
不  很显然  他是中枪后掉下来的
No. Clearly, he was shot out of it.
圣诞节的战争啊
Talk about a war on Christmas.
或者他就是在飞机上被枪杀后被扔了下来
Or he was just shot in an aircraft and pushed out.
还有其它情况吗
So we have anything else?
还有这个  嵌在衣服里的
Just this... embedded in his suit.
一小块颜料
A chip of paint
或是某种瓷釉  樱桃红的
or some kind of enamel, cherry red.
雪橇车上的
From a sleigh.
这我还不知道
I don't know yet.
一会送去实验室检查
I'm sending it down to the lab for analysis.
很可能是雪橇车上的
Probably from a sleigh.
我们对他的身份还是没有一点头绪吗
Are we any closer to figuring out who he is?
现在有了
We are now.
他叫艾德蒙德·史密斯  住在布朗克斯
Name's Edmund Smith. Lives in the Bronx.
我在鞋店查到了他的身份
I got his I.D. from that boot shop.
不好意思  你难道是专程来给我这个的吗
I'm sorry. You just came all the way down here to give me this?
是啊  你不是说过一有消息就要通知你吗
Yeah. I mean, you told me to keep you posted.
你说过的吧
You did say that, right?
好吧  我和卡塞尔要去那里
You know what? Uh, Castle and I are gonna go and check out
看看有没有什么线索
the place and see what there is to see.
好吧
Okay.
哈维  你什么时候也开始喷香水上班了
Javi, since when did you start wearing cologne to work?
这不是节日嘛
Oh, you know, well, it's the holidays,
我有应酬  有朋友要见
and I've got places to be, people to see.
你呢
How about you?
行了  我知道怎么回事了
Okay. I see where this is going.
我得就此打住
I'm gonna stop you right there.
圣诞夜我已经有安排了
I already have plans for Christmas Eve.
我要和我的女朋友们一起过
I'm hanging out with my girlfriends.
哦  挺好的
Oh. That's cool.
那之后  说不定我们可以...
Maybe afterwards, you and I can--
哈维  我们别像那些悲催绝望的假日搭档一样
Javi, let's not be one of those sad, desperate holiday hookups.
但等一切都平静下来
But when all this dies down,
如果你还想在一起
if you still want to get together,
给我打个电话就行
just give me a call.
我想他不在家
Um, I-I don't think he's home.
纽约警察  这里有没有管理员
NYPD. Is there a super or someone
可以让我们进去
that can let us into this apartment?
我们有钥匙
Yeah, um, we have a key.
蒂姆  把艾德家的钥匙拿来好吗
Tim, can you grab Ed's key?
艾德蒙德出什么事了吗
Did, uh, something happen to Edmund?
你最后一次见他是什么时候
So when was the last time you saw him?
应该是昨天晚上5点左右
Well, it must have been last night around 5:00.
我看见他带着道具包离开
Uh, I saw him leave with his costume bag.
我猜他是出去干活了
I figured he was going on a job.
艾德是个职业圣诞老人
Ed was a professional Santa.
看来他对他的工作很认真
Looks like he took his job pretty seriously.
他真是以此为生
Oh, he lived it, really.
他会无偿去休闲中心和庇护所扮演圣诞老人
I mean, volunteering at the rec center and the shelter.
他也一直陪着蒂姆和我的孩子们
He was always here for Tim and the kids.
他甚至还帮我们打官司
He--he even helped with our lawsuit.
他即是圣诞老人又是律师吗
He was a santa and a lawyer?
不  我们失去了我们的房子
No, um, we lost our house,
他正在帮助我们解决
and he was just trying to help us out.
他就是这样的人
He was like that.
看来他融入了很多人的生活
Sounds like he got involved in a lot of people's lives.
你觉得他有仇敌吗
Do you think he made any enemies along the way?
应该没有  不过上星期
I didn't think so, but then last week,
我听到有个人在敲艾德的门
I heard this man pounding on Ed's door,
还骂着很多难听的话
shouting cuss words.
你看见是谁了吗
Did you see who it was?
我看到了  我出来看了一下
I did. I-I looked out.
是个看起来挺粗暴的老头
It was an--an older, tough-looking dude.
他看到我说
When he saw me, he said,
你告诉艾德  要是再让我看见  他就死定了
"You tell Ed if I see him again, I'll kill him."
于是我告诉了艾德
So I-I told Ed.
他什么反应
How did he react?
他叫我们别担心
Well, he told us not to worry,
但能看得出来  他挺心烦的
but you could tell he was pretty shaken up.
你能描述一下他吗
You think you could describe him?
知道吗  不需要描述  这就是他
You know what? I-I don't have to. That's him.
不管他是谁  他是个飞行员
Well, whoever he is, he's a pilot.
根据在塞斯纳飞机公司的尾号登记
According to the tail number on that Cessna...
飞机的注册姓名是大卫·邓恩
the plane is registered to a David Dunne.
这家伙还有前科
Guy's got priors, too--
酒后闹事  打人
Drunk and disorderly, assault.
我们能在哪里找到他
Where do we find him?
这里只有他的公司地址
Well, this just lists his place of employment.
运河街1215号  二楼
1215 Canal Street, second floor.
看来真有人认真对待圣诞节呢
Wow. Someone takes christmas seriously.
你该去我家看看
Oh, you should see our place.
我们的圣诞树是15英尺高的冷杉
Our tree is a 15-foot noble fir,
我们的花环是从加拿大边境
We have our garland shipped in
某个我念不出来的湖那里运过来的
from some lake I can't pronounce by the Canadian border,
你还得瞧瞧我的小火车
And wait till you see my train set.
是啊  迫不及待
Yeah. Can't wait.
-你好  -圣诞快乐
- Hi. - Merry christmas.
我们来找大卫·邓恩
We're looking for David Dunne.
大卫正在大教室上课呢
Oh, Dave's in the big room teaching a class.
你们这里到底是干什么的
Uh, what is it you do here exactly?
我们创造奇迹
We make magic.
吼  吼  吼
Ho! Ho! Ho!
再来一次
Again!
吼  吼  吼
Ho! Ho! Ho!
再来
Again!
吼  吼  吼
Ho! Ho! Ho!
再来一次  丹田发声
Once again from the diaphragm.
吼  吼  吼
Ho! Ho! Ho!
棒极了
Outstanding!
圣诞老人学校吗
Santa school?
我敢打赌你们少了一个圣诞老人
And I bet you one Santa is missing.
吼  吼  吼
Ho! Ho! Ho!
太疯狂了  我没杀艾德蒙德
This is crazy. I did not kill Edmund.
相信我  这种老套说辞
Trust me. You're gonna have to do
可没法说服她
a lot better than that to convince her.
你可以从你的上次飞行说起
You can start by telling us when you last flew your plane.
好几个星期没飞了  你们可以查
Not for weeks. You can check.
我们会查的  昨晚9点半你在哪里
We intend to. Now where were you at 9:30 last night?
我在哈莱姆青少年活动中心
I was at the Harlem Youth Center
给孩子们发礼物
handing out gifts to kids.
我没见过艾德蒙德
I wasn't anywhere near Edmund.
可你在他的公寓表现得可不太像圣诞老人
But you did engage in some un-santa-like behavior at his apartment.
是为了这事啊
That what this is about?
根本没事
That was nothing.
你威胁说要杀了他  而他现在死了
You threatened to kill him, and now he's dead.
我可不觉得那叫没事
I wouldn't call that nothing.
我能解释
I can explain that, okay?
艾德蒙德抢走了我最好的一份工作
See, Edmund took one of my best gigs.
卡地亚的平面广告
It was a print AD for Cartier.
我是他们最好的圣诞老人
I was their go-to Santa.
知道吗  今年他们想要更和气更可爱的圣诞老人
You know, this year they wanted to go more warm and cuddly.
看看我  我很和气  也很可爱
Well, look at me. I-I'm warm. I'm cuddly.
但是  不  他们选择了艾德蒙德
But, no. They chose Edmund.
没错  我是喝了不少薄荷杜松子酒
So, yeah, I drank too much peppermint schnapps
去到他的公寓  怒气冲冲地胡说
and went over to his place and popped off.
我也很惭愧
I'm not proud of it,
但仅此而已
but that was all I did.
之后你有见过他吗
Did you see him again after that?
没有  你们得理解
No. You have to understand,
五年前  当我第一次遇到艾德蒙德
when I first met Edmund five years ago,
他正处于人生最低谷
he was at a low point in life.
是我帮助了他  教给他我所知道的一切
I raised him up. I taught him everything I knew.
是我把他变成了世界级的圣诞老人
I turned him into a world-class Santa,
而现在我反而还因他丢了工作
and now I'm losing gigs to him?
也许这就是命
Well, maybe that's it.
也许是时候摘下这顶毛绒绒的红色内裤了
Maybe it's time to hang up the fluffy red jockstrap.
这是打比方还是你真的...
Is... Is that a metaphor or do you really--
艾德蒙德被害的时候
Uh, when Edmund was killed,
他还穿着圣诞老人服装
he was wearing his Santa suit.
你知道昨晚他有工作吗
Do you know if he had a job last night?
你得去问问他的经纪人
You'd have to ask his agent.
圣诞老人还有经纪人
Santas have agents?
对  我们大多用的是贝荷经纪公司
Yeah. Mostly we use the Bells & Holly agency.
你刚才说艾德蒙德处于人生的低谷
You said Edmund was at a low point in his life.
那话是什么意思
What did you mean by that?
我只是觉得  他做圣诞老人是想改变自己的人生
I just think he became a Santa to turn his life around.
事实上也确实成功了
And it worked, too.
改变他的人生
Turn his life around?
他之前招了什么麻烦吗
Was he in trouble of some sort?
我只知道  在我刚认识艾德蒙德时
All I know is, back when I met him,
他与现在判若两人
Edmund was a totally different guy.
大卫·邓恩的不在场证明已证实
David Dunne's alibi checked out.
哈勒姆青少年俱乐部说他昨晚的确在那
Harlem Youth Club said that he was there last night.
他的飞机也至少有一个月没起飞过了
And the Cessna has been parked in a hangar for over a month.
你知道艾德蒙德接了什么扮演圣诞的活吗
Did you find out what Santa job Edmund was doing?
他的经纪公司说昨晚他并没有活动
His agency said he wasn't booked on any gigs last night.
那他为什么会穿道具服呢
So then why was he wearing his Santa suit
以及他是怎么死的
and how'd he end up dead?
如果这是个故事
Well, if this was a story,
我们是不是应该先弄清这个角色的背景
it would all come back to Edmund's character..
他为什么会去做圣诞老人呢
why he became a Santa in the first place.
结果  这也是个谜
Turns out, that's a mystery all by itself.
我一直在查他的历史资料  你们看
I've been looking into this guy, and check it.
这就是我们的圣诞老人五年前的样子
That is Santa five years ago.
见见詹姆斯·艾德蒙德·史密斯
Meet James Edmund Smith.
他曾是一家大公司的私人股权经理人
He was a private equity manager at some big firm.
-他俩是同一个人  -对
- That's the same guy? - Yeah.
期间出了什么事
What happened?
将自己完全奉献给工作
Dedication to his craft.
就像《愤怒的公牛》里的罗伯特·德尼罗
Like De Niro in "Raging Bull."
扮演圣诞老人吗
To be a Santa?
我知道  差距太大了  还有你们更想不到的
It's pretty extreme, I know, and I'll tell you this much,
他去扮演圣诞老人不是为了赚钱
he didn't go all Santa for the money.
以前在公司的时候  他一年能挣50万
Back in the day, he used to pull down a half a million a year.
扮圣诞老人  只能挣到原来的十分之一
As Santa, he made a tenth of that.
扮圣诞老人能挣那么多呀
You make that much as a Santa?
也许我也该换换工作了
Maybe I should switch jobs, huh?
你想增重180斤然后搞一堆裹着脏尿布的
What, gain 200 pounds and have a bunch of rug rats
死小鬼坐在你腿上啊
sitting on your lap with dirty diapers?
谢谢你描述的画面
Yeah, thanks for that visual.
还有件事
Oh, here's another thing.
我查了一下艾德蒙德的账户
I pulled Edmund's financials.
被杀那天晚上
On the night he was killed,
他曾从自动取款机里提了2000块钱
he withdrew 2 grand from his ATM.
但尸体并没有携带任何现金
He didn't have that money on him when we found him.
他的钱包是空的
His wallet was empty.
好吧  去查查取款机的监视录像
All right, take a look at the ATM footage
看看有没有人跟他在一起
and see if anyone was with him.
他有可能遭抢了
He might have been robbed.
遇到强盗然后被发射上天吗
Robbed and then launched into space?
难道这个的可信度会比你的雪橇理论低
And how is that less plausible than your sleigh?
我认为你是在说"合理度"
I think you mean less clausible.
他的通话记录有线索吗
What about his phone records?
给一个布鲁克林的律师打了一堆电话
Made a bunch of calls to some lawyer in Brooklyn.
但这条才是最有意思的
But here's the interesting one.
他的最后一个电话是打给前妻的
Last phone call he ever made was to his ex-wife.
-圣诞婆婆   -格文·哈文
- Mrs. Claus. - Gwenn Harwin.
我查了他长期的通话记录
I went back pretty far in his phone records.
至少在近三年内  他从没给她打过电话
He hasn't called her for at least three years.
这么说  他取了2000块钱  致电前妻
So he pulls out 2 grand, calls his ex-wife,
几小时之后  被人发现已死亡
and a couple of hours later, he ends up dead?
传她来问话
Let's bring her in.
他打电话来说想过来看看
He called me to say that he wanted to stop by.
非常奇怪
It was the strangest thing.
等他到了之后  我都认不出他来了
When he showed up, I didn't recognize him,
而现在  他就这么去了
and now he's just... gone.
很抱歉  哈文女士  但我必须问你
I'm sorry to ask you this, Ms. Harwin,
昨晚九点半你在哪里
but where were you last night at 9:30?
没关系  我完全理解
That's quite all right. I understand.
当时我在主持一个食物银行的募捐活动
I was, uh, hosting a benefit for the food bank.
艾德蒙德去找你是为了什么
And why did Edmund come to see you?
为了道歉
To apologize.
为什么要道歉
Apologize for what?
为他离开家的方式道歉
For the way he walked out on our life.
我们曾经很和谐  至少我是这么想的
We were good together. At least, I thought we were.
十二年的婚姻
12 years of marriage,
一起创造的生活
of building a life together,
五年前的平安夜里
and then five years ago Christmas Eve,
我俩一起参加了一个派对  之后
we went to a party, and afterwards,
我们一起通宵观看《美妙人生》
we stayed up to watch "It's A Wonderful Life."
第二天一早  他就离开了
And the next morning, he left
穿上衣服就走
with just the shirt on his back
没有一句解释
and no explanation.
但他为什么会选现在去看你
But why would he visit you now?
他想让我知道  他为自己离开的方式
He wanted me to know how sorry he was
感到很抱歉  以防将来...
for the way he left in case...
他出什么事
anything happened to him.
他那是什么意思
What did he mean by that?
我也不知道
I don't know what he meant.
我根本不认识他了
I-I didn't even know who this man was.
他看起来很紧张  几乎随时可能崩溃
He seemed very nervous and very on edge.
他有跟你暗示是什么事或人
Did he give you any indication
使他感到害怕
of what he was afraid of
或可能伤害他吗
or who might have been after him?
他出门后  我在窗口
After he left, I went to the window
目送他上计程车
to watch him get into the cab.
车开走之后
And as the cab pulled away,
我看到一个骑摩托车的人在跟着他
there was a man on a motorcycle who was following him.
我们需要你详细描述一下那辆摩托车
We're gonna need you to give us a description of that motorcycle
和骑车人
along with its rider.
提前要给珍妮的圣诞礼物吗
Early Christmas present from Jenny?
算是吧  请你不要乱动好吗
Something like that. Would you mind not touching it?
看呀看呀
Well, well, well.
这下我算是明白你跟珍妮
Now I see what you and Jenny
平安夜有什么计划了
got planned for Christmas Eve.
你们要忙上好一阵咯
Y'all gon' be getting busy.
吼  吼
Ho! Ho!
吼
Ho!
我会把你这个行为看作是为了破案的努力
I take it this is your idea of working the Santa case?
埃斯波西托警探
Detective Esposito,
你现在不是该在查自动取款机的监视录像吗
you're supposed to be digging up that ATM footage.
还有你
And you are?
我该查死者常联系的那个律师的背景  长官
Chasing down that lawyer that our victim had been calling, Sir.
好吧  别在这儿瞎闹了
Okay, then. Let's finish up this hoochie-coochie thing
快干活去
and get on with it.
遵命
Yes, Sir.
被撞个正着
So busted.
骑摩托车的人与艾德蒙德
How does "guy on a motorcycle"
在公园"着陆"有什么关联呢
connect to Edmund landing in the park?
没什么关联
Nothing connects.
为什么一个人之前还在看圣诞电影
Why does a man watch a Christmas movie
看完了就抛弃一切去扮圣诞老人了呢
then walk out on everything to become a Santa?
除非艾德蒙德事件的关键点就是
Unless the key to Edmund's story
《美妙人生》
is "It's A Wonderful Life."
你记不记得  影片中
You remember, in the movie,
乔治·贝里试图在平安夜自杀
George Bailey tried to commit suicide on Christmas Eve
然后有个天使救了他
and was saved by an angel?
在我们的事件里  这个天使就是大卫·邓恩
Which in our story is David Dunne.
这选角选得真奇怪
Weird casting choice, I know,
但如果艾德蒙德那时正想"摆脱现状"
but what if Edmund was trying to jump off a metaphoric bridge,
你懂的  就是重新开始
you know, to start over?
当圣诞老人吗
As a Santa?
是的
Yes.
没错  这确实不太说得通
Yeah, that's where it falls apart.
事实上  艾德蒙德可不仅仅
Actually, it looks like Edmund was way more
是个圣诞老人
than just a Santa.
我终于查到
I finally got ahold of that lawyer
他常联系的那个律师了
that he'd been calling.
她代理卡伯特家对一间专放高利贷的公司
She'd actually filed a suit on behalf of his neighbors,
提出诉讼  那家公司叫日湾信贷
the Cabots, who'd lost their home to a predatory lender,
他们收走了卡伯特一家的房子
Sun Cove Funding.
起诉理由是一些非法交易
Something about illegal practices
和造假的文件
and forged documents.
总之是一次集体诉讼
Anyway, it's a class-action suit
代表43个家庭的利益  成败牵涉好几百万美元
representing 43 families with millions of dollars at stake.
但为什么会是艾德蒙德给律师打电话呢
But why was Edmund calling the lawyer?
她致力于意外事故案件
She had been working on contingency.
为了跟这个案子已经耗掉了大笔的钱
She's already lost tons of money
所以她想放弃诉讼
pressing the case, so she wanted to drop the suit.
但艾德蒙德求她不要放弃
But Edmund begged her not to.
事实上  他请她只要拖延几天
In fact, he asked her to hold off just a few days,
或许他就能力挽狂澜了
maybe he could turn things around.
怎么做
How?
他没说  但是她告诉他
Well, he didn't say, but she told him
唯一可以力挽狂澜的
the only thing that would turn things around
是两万五千美金的支票
was a check for 25 grand.
对艾德蒙德要告的公司
What do we know about this company
我们了解多少
that Edmund was up against?
日湾吗  就是个皮包公司
SunCove? It's a FLY-BY-NIGHT.
他们收了钱  然后就倒闭
They made their money, then they folded.
盖茨正好在证监会里有朋友
Gates actually has a friend at the S.E.C.
正在查关于他们的信息
Trying to dig up some information on them.
你去联系一下诈骗调查组
Can you check with the fraud division?
看看他们对日湾了解多少
See what they know about SunCove?
-明白  -谢谢
- Yeah. You got it. - Thanks.
说到《美妙人生》
Speaking of "It's a wonderful life,"
我在想  明晚
I was thinking, tomorrow night,
我们可以搞个圣诞电影马拉松  或者
perhaps we should have a christmas movie marathon or...
来场让生活更美妙的马拉松
some other kind of marathon that makes life wonderful.
怎么了
What?
卡塞尔  我知道节日对你来说很重要
Castle, look, I know how much the holidays mean to you
我也知道你爱圣诞节
and I know that you love Christmas,
但我明天不能陪你了
But I can't make it tomorrow.
什么
What?
分局人手不够
The precinct is short staffed,
所以我得留下来工作
so I'm gonna have to work.
怎么  那个什么
How--to--what--don't--
这种差事不是应该新人做吗
Don't...don't you have seniority?
怎么会这样
Don't...how... how can this happen?
听着  我
Look, I...
我不能告诉盖茨
I couldn't tell Gates.
她不知道我们的事  好吗
She doesn't know about us, okay?
对不起  我知道你很失望
So... look, I'm sorry. I know that you're disappointed.
不  不
No. Ah... no.
这不是你的错  我懂的
I...it's not your fault. I know.
没事的  我...
It's all...it's okay. I'm...
我还是走吧  跟阿丽克西斯约好了
I gotta get outta here anyway. I got a date with Alexis.
一起去圣诞扫货
Gonna do some christmas shopping.
-玩得开心点  -好的
- Okay, have fun. - Okay.
-不用给我买东西了  -行
- And don't get me anything. - Right.
我从取款机的监控录像里找到了这个
So, uh, I pulled this from the A.T.M. Footage.
艾德蒙德取钱的时候是一个人
Edmund was alone when he took out the cash,
但他确实上了一辆出租车
but he did get into a cab.
知道他去哪了吗
Any idea where he was going?
我通过执照牌追踪到了他坐的出租车
Yeah, I traced the taxi he used from the medallion.
司机说他去了霍霍库斯机场
Cabbie said that he took Edmund to Ho-Ho-Kus field.
是新泽西的一家小型机场
It's a small airfield out in Jersey.
他是从那里起飞的吗
Is that where he got on the plane?
你觉得呢  但其实不是
You'd think, but no.
司机说
The cabbie said that
艾德蒙德让他稍等  自己要去跟别人碰头
Edmund had him wait so he could go meet somebody,
然后他回到车内  他们离开了机场
then he got back in the cab, they left the airfield,
后来他在长岛下了车
and the cabbie dropped him off in Long Island city.
这说不通啊
That doesn't make any sense.
如果他去了长岛  最后又怎么到了天上
How'd he end up in the air if he went to Long Island city?
我不知道
I have no idea,
不过跟他在机场碰头的人也许知道
but the person he met with at the airfield might.
那么说来
So...
你又要值圣诞班了
You, uh, pulled the Christmas shift again?
你不该在旁边偷听的
You know, you shouldn't be eavesdropping, buddy.
埃斯波  你看那是不是樱桃红
Espo, does that look cherry red to you?
是的
It does.
跟我们在艾德蒙德身上发现的掉漆一样
Just like the paint chip we found on Edmund.
锁被撬过了
This lock's been tampered with.
看起来是被强行打开的
Looks like it was forced open.
这里有没干的血迹
There's fresh blood here.
还有不少
And lots of it.
貌似我们找到犯罪现场了
Looks like we just found our crime scene.
是的
Yeah.
血和艾德蒙德的吻合
Well, it looks like the blood is a match to Edmund,
但目前为止  没有找到指纹
But so far, there are no prints.
驾驶舱好像被清理过了
Looks like the cockpit's been wiped.
如果艾德蒙德从这里下车
If Edmund came down here
然后又回到长岛
and then he went back to Long Island city,
那他怎么会死在这架直升机里
then how the hell did he end up in this chopper?
不管谁跟他在一起  都脱不了干系
Well, whoever was with him has gotta have the answer to that.
我们从机主查起
Let's start with who owns this thing.
据机场管理员玛吉先生所说
Well, according to the airfield manager, Mr. Mudge,
它属于一个叫查克·埃姆斯的人
It belongs to a Chuck Ames,
但他正在夏威夷度假
But he's on vacation in hawaii.
你好  玛吉先生
Hi, Mr. Mudge.
谁还有授权  能开那架飞机
Now is anyone else authorized to fly that bird?
据我所知没有
Not that I'm aware of.
貌似谁都能
Looks like just about anybody
进入这个机场
can have access to this airfield.
没有检查关卡  没有监控探头
There's no checkpoints, no cameras.
在此之前我们根本不需要
We never needed any till now.
关键是  如果有人上了这架飞机
The point is, if someone did get on to this property,
要把它开走有多难
how hard would it be for them to fly that chopper outta here?
任何有飞行执照的人都能开
Anybody with a helicopter rating could take it up.
R-44很容易驾驭
R-44 is easy.
甚至都不需要钥匙
You don't even need a key to start it.
我们在找一个
So then we're looking for someone
熟悉这个机场内部的人
that knew the ins and outs of this airport
这个人知道直升机在这里
Along with the fact that that chopper was gonna be here.
这个人甚至知道查克·埃姆斯
Maybe even someone who knew
在夏威夷
that Chuck Ames was gonna be in hawaii.
我们需要埃姆斯先生的联系方式
We're gonna need Mr. Ames' contact info
还有你们所有员工的资料
along with the names of all of your employees
还有去年所有在这里飞行过的人
and everyone who's flown through here in the past year.
我还有圣诞彩灯要挂
Hey, I-I got Christmas lights to hang.
知道  我们还有凶案要破
Yeah, and we have a murder to solve.
能不能知道
Now is there any way to know
直升机昨晚在哪飞
where the chopper flew last night?
有没有飞行记录  GPS系统
Is there a flight recorder, GPS system?
再说一遍  它是架低端直升机
Again, she's a low-tech bird.
你们有燃耗记录吗
Do you have a record of the fuel that was in the tank?
燃料记录显示是满的
Fuel log says it was full.
我们可以通过燃油消耗量
We can figure out how far the chopper flew
推知直升机飞行了多远
by how much fuel was used.
油箱里少了五分之一的油
It was down about a fifth of a tank.
R-44耗油约
The R-44 burns about
四或五英里每加仑
4 or 5 miles per gallon,
所以它飞了大概45英里
so it flew about 45 miles.
差不多就是
That's almost exactly
这里到长岛一个来回的距离
how far it is to Long Island city and back.
艾德蒙德在那里下了出租车
Edmund took the cab there
然后上了直升机
and must have gotten in that chopper.
好的  我们去查一下长岛
Okay, let's check all the heliports
所有的停机坪  找出是在哪儿降落的
In Long Island city and find out where.
我是说  圣诞老人被杀已经够糟的了
I mean, it's bad enough Santa has been murdered.
这还将是18年来
This will be the first Christmas Eve
我们不在一起过的第一个圣诞夜
In 18 years we haven't spent together.
这开启了一个糟糕的先例
I mean, it sets a grim precedent.
老爸  你说得太夸张了
Dad, you're being dramatic.
你随时都可以见朋友啊
Well, you can see your friends anytime.
如果只是"一个"朋友呢
Well... what if it's just one person,
而且他其实不是"朋友"
and he's not really a friend?
新男友  好吧
Oh, a new guy. Okay.
那么
Well, does this, uh,
那"一个"不是"朋友"的人叫啥
Non-plural non-friend have a name?
-他叫麦克斯  -麦克斯
- It's max. - Max.
我在年度烂诗比赛上遇到他的
I met him at the annual bad poetry contest
就在感恩节前
right before Thanksgiving.
这样啊
I see.
带他来咱家  我很乐意见见这位下乘的诗人
Well, bring him along. I would love to meet this bad poet.
-平安夜来见家长  -是啊
- Uh, y--meet my dad on Christmas Eve? - Yeah.
这样压力太大了
Tha-that's way too much pressure.
有什么压力  吃吃喝喝  高高兴兴吗
What pr--pressure to what, eat, drink, and be merry?
这会...
It'll be--
圣诞节当天麦克斯要和家人去伦敦
Max is going to London with his family on Christmas day.
假期结束我才能见到他
I won't get to see him till after break.
我们就想去公园溜冰
We just want to go ice skating in the park.
好  当然  去吧
Yeah. Of course. Of course. Go.
玩得开心点
Have a great time.
再说你要和贝克特一起过嘛
Besides, you'll be with Beckett.
对
Right.
别担心
Oh, and don't worry.
我会在圣诞老人来之前就回来睡觉的
I'll be home in bed before Santa comes.
好吧
Right.
盖茨警监
Oh, Captain Gates.
干什么
Y-yes, what is it?
我想让你在去度假前
I just wanted to make sure that you got this
收到这个礼物
before you took off for the holidays.
谢谢你  卡塞尔
Well, thank you, Mr. Castle.
对不起
Oh, I-I'm sorry.
我没为你准备礼物
I don't have anything for you.
每天能来这里就是你给我的礼物了
Please. Just being here each day is gift.
我想让你知道  我万分感谢
I just wanted to let you know how much I appreciate
你们所做的一切
all that you do,
你和贝克特探长
you and detective Beckett.
卡塞尔先生  我要去郊区
Mr. Castle, I am on my way uptown
见我的婆婆
to meet my mother-in-law
和她一起喝茶  吃那些小小的可怕的三明治
to have tea and eat those tiny freakin' sandwiches.
所以不如你直说你到底打什么注意吧
So why don't you just say what's on your mind?
我就是很担心贝克特探长
I'm just so worried about detective Beckett.
她工作太努力了
I mean, she works so hard.
你不觉得她应该享受假期吗
Don't you think she deserves a little holiday?
难道没有其他人可以帮她顶上
Isn't there someone else who could take
平安夜的班吗
that Christmas Eve shift?
首先  我怎么安排人手
First of all, how I schedule my people
和你没关系
is not your concern.
不过话说回来
And having said that,
贝克特探长自愿要上这轮班
detective Beckett volunteered to take the shift.
她什么时候要求的
When did she do that?
今天早些时候
Earlier today.
她来找我  要求帮埃尔丁警探代班
She came to me and asked to take Detective Eldin's shift.
他结婚了  但她没有
He has a family, and she doesn't.
那好吧
Okay, then.
问题解决
Problem solved.
好  这样就将范围缩小到了长岛
Okay, so that narrows it down to five heliports
五个直升机停机坪
in Long Island City.
一个是警局  一个是医院
One is a police station. One's a hospital.
这两处都有监控  排除后就只有公司大楼的
They'd both be monitored, so that leaves helipads at
直升机停机坪了
bankcorp building,
一处是西部酒店  凯斯商务大楼
one West Hotel, and Case Commerce Building.
凯斯商务  CC
Case Commerce... C.C.
拐杖糖
The candy canes.
凯斯商务  CC
Case Commerce. C.C.
那就是艾德蒙德死前去的地方
That's where Edmund was.
我们去查清楚吧
Let's find out why.
卡塞尔
Hey, Castle.
你一起来吗
You coming?
当然
Yeah, sure.
你逃不掉的
Oh, you can't escape it.
到处都是圣诞气氛
Christmas is everywhere.
想过个开心的节日压力好大
So much pressure to have a good time.
你还好吧
Are you okay?
我能有啥不好的
Why wouldn't I be?
凯斯商务  到了
Case Commerce. There it is.
你好  这里怎么了
Hi. Wait, uh, what's going on here?
貌似在昨晚的办公室圣诞派对上发生了
Looks like a heist occurred at the office Christmas party
-抢劫  -抢劫
- last night. - A heist?
直到今天早上
Well, I-I didn't notice
我才发现有东西失踪了
anything was missing until this morning.
随后我就打电话报警了
And that's when I called you people.
昨晚的派对上你不会碰巧请了圣诞老人吧
You didn't happen to have a Santa working your party, did you?
是啊  我们请了
Yes, we did.
他看起来是这样吗
Did he look like this?
是的
Yes.
他就是我们的圣诞老人  怎么了
He was our Santa. Why?
看来我们的圣诞老人很淘气啊
Looks like our Santa was a little more naughty than nice.
没有  昨晚我是第一次见到他
No, I never saw him before last night.
我也没意识到他偷了东西
And I wasn't aware he'd stolen anything.
但是鉴于我们的工作
But given what we do here,
我想这还不算是最糟糕的
I suppose it could've been a lot worse.
凯斯先生  你的公司是做什么的
And what is it that your company does, Mr. Case?
投资服务  主要是资产管理
Investment services. Asset management mostly.
考虑到我们有许多客户和账户的信息
Given the amount of client and account information,
对身份窃贼来说我们可是一座金矿
we'd be a gold mine for identity thieves.
但是这些系统没有被动过
None of those systems were touched.
那他们偷了什么呢
So what did they steal?
他后面办公室里的一个钟
A clock from his office in back.
抱歉  你说的是"钟"
I'm sorry. Did you just say "Clock"?
探长  那可不是随便的一个钟
Not just any clock, Detective.
托马斯·蒂莱吉早期作品
An early Tomas Tilledge.
复兴时期的传奇钟表匠
Legendary clockmaker from the Restoration period.
一定非常值钱吧
That must have been worth a great deal.
估值为三万美金
I had it appraised at $30,000.
多大的钟
Wow. How big was it?
差不多这么大
It's about this size.
很小  能装进他的麻袋里
Small enough to fit in his sack.
你知道  很难相信我的客人中
You know, it's hard enough imagining
会有人是小偷  但是圣诞老人
one of my guests being a thief, but Santa?
你确定没有其他东西失踪吗
Are you sure that nothing else is missing?
确定  怎么了
Positive. Why?
因为我们有证据表明你的圣诞老人
Well, because our evidence suggests that your Santa
是乘着停在你们停机坪的直升飞机离开的
left by helicopter, which was waiting on your helipad.
他为什么要乘直升飞机
Why would he take a helicopter?
你们在派对上没听到什么声音吗
You didn't hear anything from the party?
没有  但是音乐声很大
No, but the music was loud,
而且后壁是隔音的
and the back wall is soundproofed.
那个钟还有什么特别之处吗
Was there anything else that was special about this clock?
据我所知是没有
Not that I'm aware of.
我会让一名警探
Okay, I'm gonna get one of my detectives
过来和你的员工谈谈
to come down and interview your staff.
同时  能给我一份
In the meantime, could I have a list
出席派对的名单吗
of all of the party attendees?
-好  -当然可以
- Sure. - Of course.
我们也需要电梯监控录像
We'll also pull elevator footage
以防有未受邀请的客人参加
to make sure that there weren't any uninvited guests.
三万
$30,000.
仅比卡伯特一家需要的诉讼费多一点而已
That's a little more than the Cabots needed for their lawsuit.
也许我们的圣诞老人是个罗宾汉
Maybe our Santa is Robin Hood,
劫富济贫
stealing from the rich to give to the poor?
但是他为什么要用直升飞机偷这个呢
Yeah, but why would he use a helicopter to steal this?
他本可以把它塞进麻袋里
I mean, he could've just stuffed it in his sack
然后笑呵呵地离开那里
and ho-ho-ho'ed outta there.
一定不仅仅是因为钟的关系
It has to be about more than just the clock.
在他的工作台后面还有一些钟
Well, there were a couple more clocks on his workbench.
也许这一个有什么特别意义
Maybe this one's significant somehow.
好吧  你的理论是什么
Okay. What's your theory?
里面有藏宝图
Uh... treasure map inside.
不对
No.
不对  这个钟是被一个秘密组织用来
No. The clock was commissioned by a secret society
倒数世界末日的
to count down the end of days--
一个由圣诞老人组成的秘密组织
A secret society of Santas,
他们守护着时间
who are the guardians of time.
这想法太拉风了
Oh, that's good.
先不管直升飞机之谜
Okay, putting aside the mystery of the helicopter,
假设这跟钟有关
let's say it is about the clock.
艾德蒙德是怎么知道的
How did Edmund know about it?
办公室里没人认识他
Nobody from the office recognized him.
也许他之前办过派对
Well, maybe he had worked the party before.
抱歉  老兄  我查过了
Sorry, bro. I checked.
他没有
He hasn't,
但他绝对打算今年去
but he sure was determined to work it this year.
那家机构预约了另外一个圣诞老人
The agency had booked another Santa to work that party,
但凯斯商务中有人
But someone from case commerce
一周前打电话取消了预约
called about a week ago to cancel.
让我猜猜  不是凯斯公司的人打的电话
Let me guess. No one actually called from case.
-正解  -当他到达的时候
- Ding ding. - And when he arrived,
他们以为他就是受雇的圣诞老人
they assumed he was the Santa they'd hired.
真是高明的诡计啊
Kind of a brilliant scam, really.
你可以进入上层家庭和高级企业
You have access to high-end homes and businesses,
再说谁会怀疑圣诞老人呢
and who's gonna distrust Santa?
显然  他的同伴们就会
Uh, his partners, apparently.
盗亦无道  即使是"圣盗"
No honor among thieves, even Santa thieves.
让劫案科把那张照片发到当铺
All right. Have robbery send that photo to pawnshops
和各大拍卖行
and auction houses.
如果他的同伴想兑换成现金  立刻通知我
If his partners try to cash in, I want to know.
好的
Absolutely.
一个人抛弃自己的生活和高新职位
A man leaves his life and a high-paying job
成为邻里间的老好人
to become the neighborhood saint
结果却因盗窃一个钟而被枪杀
only to get shot dead after stealing a clock
那钟还不如随便一辆车值钱
that's worth less than your average car,
然后他又被扔出直升机
and then he gets thrown out of a helicopter
而他最开始根本就不需要上那架直升机
that he didn't even need to be in in the first place.
完全说不通嘛
It makes no sense.
鉴于我们手中对那家伙的全部信息
Given everything that we know about this guy,
整件事都与他的为人完全不符
this is completely out of character.
有时候人就是会做一些让外人难以理解的事
Well, sometimes people do inexplicable things.
任何事都是有缘由的
There's an explanation for everything.
是吗
Is there?
你主动要求替埃尔丁值班
You volunteered to take Eldin's shift.
别找理由
Don't pretend.
如果你还没准备好  为什么不直接告诉我
If you aren't ready, why not just tell me?
我很抱歉  卡塞尔  我不是有意...
I'm sorry, Castle. I didn't mean to--
你不是有意什么
You didn't mean to what?
圣诞节对我和对你的意义完全不一样
Christmas means something different to me than it does to you.
都是圣诞节嘛  能有多不一样
It's Christmas. I mean, how can it be different?
卡塞尔  每年冬天  一旦寒冷袭来
Castle, every winter, as soon as that chill rolls in,
我就仿佛又置身于那条小巷
I am right back there in that alley.
到1月9日  我们却仍未摘下
January 9th, and we still haven't taken
圣诞节的各种装饰品
our Christmas decorations down.
等我和我爸终于摘下来的时候
And by the time my dad and I did,
就好像我们把圣诞节永远封存了
it was like we were putting Christmas away forever.
我们自那之后再没打开过那些盒子
We haven't opened those boxes since.
我不知道
I didn't know.
所以  每一年我爸都会去他的小木屋
That's why, every year, my dad goes up to his cabin,
自从我当上了警察开始
and ever since I became a rookie,
我一直都要求在圣诞节当天值班
I have taken the Christmas shift,
因为我知道有很多家庭
because I know that there are families out there
都在合家团聚  一起庆祝节日
that are celebrating together in their homes,
我要一直守护着  那就是我的节日传统
and I am keeping watch, and that is my tradition.
而且那对我很重要
And that is important to me.
就跟你的节日传统对你很重要一样
It's as important as your tradition is to you.
我很抱歉  卡塞尔
And I'm sorry, Castle.
我之前以为我可以放下这一切
I thought I could let that go,
但我...
But I...
我理解
I understand.
听着  我找到一个管理员
Yeah, so I got a custodian
他昨晚上屋顶抽烟
who was up on the roof last night for a smoke.
他看见什么了吗
Did he see anything?
不是他看到什么  而是他发现了什么
Well, it's not what he saw. It's what he found.
那地方之前曾被清扫过
The place was cleaned earlier in the day,
但当他上去的时候
but when he got up there,
发现直升机场到处都是垃圾
there was trash blown all over the helipad,
可能是直升机起飞时机翼转动带起来的
probably from the rotor wash when it took off.
什么样的垃圾
What kind of trash?
像是等人时留下的
The kind that looked like someone had been waiting for someone,
饮料罐  糖果纸
Soda can, candy wrappers,
以及一包空的斗烟叶盒
And an empty pouch of pipe tobacco.
斗烟叶
Pipe tobacco?
我们知道有谁
Now who do we know
既用烟斗  又驾驶直升机的呢
that smokes a pipe and flies?
记住
And remember,
当你们出去工作的时候
when you go out there,
圣诞老人不是从烟囱进入人们的家里
Santa does not enter through the chimney.
而是进入人们的心里
He enters through the heart.
要不要坐直升机进入啊
What about through a helicopter?
你在干嘛呢
What are you doing?
快放下
Put that down.
你疯了吗
Are you crazy?
祝大家都圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas to all...
祝大家晚安
And to all a good night.
我已经告诉过你们当时我在哪儿
I already told you where I was,
反正不是在直升机里
and it wasn't in any helicopter.
是啊  关于那个
Yeah, about that.
我们查过了黑人区青年俱乐部的照片
We checked the photos from the harlem youth club.
那边的圣诞老人可不是你
The Santa that was there was not you.
你当晚到底在哪儿
Where were you that night, really?
我来帮你回忆一下
Let me help you.
我刚和查克·埃姆斯通完电话
I just got off of the phone with Chuck Ames,
也就是拿架直升机的主人
the guy that owns that helicopter,
他说你之前从他手中租用过
and he said that you've rented it from him before.
我是认识那家伙  那又怎样
So I know the guy. So what?
你们没有证据证明当晚我在那架直升机上
You got no proof that I was in that helicopter that night.
那是因为你还回来时  把指纹都擦干净了
That's because you wiped it down when you brought it back.
但你顺走了一些东西  不是吗
But you took something with you, didn't you?
我们在你的公寓里找到了这个
We found this in your apartment.
现在想改下你的口供吗
Care to revise your statement?
我再帮你回忆一下
Let me help you again.
艾德蒙德想出了一个
Edmund figured out a way
让你们二人迅速发家致富的方法
to make a quick score for you both.
他在派对上工作
He worked the party,
你驾驶着逃跑用的直升机
And you were the getaway flier.
等他上了直升机的时候
And then when he got back into the chopper,
你决定一个人独吞全部
you decided you wanted it all for yourself.
全部什么  他拿的不过就是个该死的钟
All what? All he had was that damn clock.
那可不是个普通的钟
Not just any clock.
托马斯·蒂莱吉的钟价值三万多美元
A Tomas Tilledge worth $30,000.
那破玩意儿值三万多吗
That crap is worth 30 grand?
你不知道吗
You didn't know that?
不  我  我没有杀他
No, I-- and I didn't kill him.
得了吧  大卫  你刚承认案发当时在现场
Come on, Dave. You just admitted to being there.
好吧  我确实在场
All right! I was there.
艾德说会付我两千块
Ed said he'd pay me 2 grand
只要我把直升机开到那栋大楼上
to fly the chopper to that building,
等着他搬上来一些东西  然后飞走
wait while he loaded something on, and take off,
装上去的可不是钟
And it wasn't no clock.
他想试试那直升机能承受多少的额外重量
He wanted to know how much extra weight the chopper could handle.
他打算装什么
What was he planning on taking?
他给了两千块  我就没多问
For 2 grand, I didn't ask.
我就把直升机开过去等着
I just flew to the helipad and waited.
然后突然间  艾德蒙德就冲了过来
Then all of a sudden, here comes Edmund,
带着钟在屋顶上跑
running out on the roof with the clock,
嘴里喊着  快走  快走
yelling, "Go! Go! Go!"
接下来我只知道  有人对我们开火
Next thing I know, we're taking fire.
-有人冲你们开枪吗  -是的
- Someone was shooting at you? - Hell, yeah.
艾德蒙德刚爬上去  就被他们射中了
They nailed Edmund just as he boarded the chopper.
你见到开枪的人了吗
Did you see who it was?
没有  当时太黑
No, it was dark.
我就赶紧起飞了
I just cowboyed the hell out of there.
可怜的艾德
But poor Ed.
我不停地喊  把该死的门关上
I kept yelling to him to close the damn door,
可等我回头看时  他已经死了
but when I turned back, he was already dead.
飞机晃得厉害  不知什么时候
The chopper banked hard. Before I knew it,
他已经不在了
he was gone.
如果大卫说的是实话
Well, if Dave is telling the truth,
那凶手就在那栋楼里
the shooter was in that building.
不只是这样
Not just in the building.
想要到达停机坪  只能通过凯斯商务
The only access to the helipad is through Case Commerce,
也就是说凶手当时就在派对上
which means our killer was at the party.
可艾德蒙德怎么会去派对
Okay, but what was Edmund doing?
他偷个那么重的东西到底要干吗
What was he planning on stealing that weighed so much?
再说他干嘛偷那破钟
And why would he take that stupid clock?
真是一团乱
It makes no sense.
现在更乱了
It makes even less sense now.
我们在查看电梯监控时
We were running through elevator security footage
发现了一个并不在
and we found one person who went up to the party
客人名单上的人
who wasn't on the guest list.
那个邻居小孩  蒂姆·卡伯特
The neighbor kid-- Tim Cabot?
看他手里的东西
And look what he's holding.
一个摩托车头盔
A motorcycle helmet.
这么说他就是那天晚上骑摩托
So he was the one that followed Edmund
跟踪艾德蒙德的人
on the motorcycle that night.
这孩子有前科
Kid's got a record, too--
破门入室  袭击他人  非法占有
B&E, assault, possession.
可他到那个地方去干吗
Yeah, but what the hell was he doing there?
我想我知道原因
I think I may have an answer.
记得那起针对日湾基金公司的集体诉讼吗
Remenber that class-action suit against SunCove Funding?
嗯
Yeah.
我让证交会的朋友帮我查到了这些
My contact at the S.E.C. dug these up.
日湾公司成立的原始条款
SunCove's original articles of incorporation,
上面有账户持有人的签名
showing the name of the account signatory.
看着眼熟吗
Look familiar?
詹姆斯·艾德蒙德·史密斯  就是死者
"James Edmund Smith," the victim.
圣诞老人就是
Santa is the shark
骗取人们房子的元凶
who bilked those people out of their homes?
他的罪过不仅限于此
He has more blood on his hands than that.
蒂姆·卡伯特的父亲死于一场车祸
Tim Cabot's father died in a car crash.
拜艾德蒙德·史密斯所赐  为了还清膨胀贷款
Fell asleep at the wheel working three jobs
他要干三份工作  最后在开车时睡着了
to pay his inflated mortgage, courtesy of Edmund Smith.
车祸发生在五年前的圣诞夜平安夜
That was Christmas Eve, five years ago.
就是艾德蒙德离开他妻子的那个圣诞节
The Christmas that Edmund walked out on his life.
这么说
So...
这是一个赎罪的故事
it's a tale of redemption.
艾德蒙德搬到了
Edmund moves next door
这个被他毁掉的家庭隔壁
to the family whose lives he destroyed,
全心全意地补偿他们
dedicating his life to repairing theirs,
没有告诉他们自己的真实身份
never telling them who he really is.
蒂姆会不会知道了他的身份
But what if Tim found out?
那这就是另一个不同的故事了
Then it's a very different tale.
很抱歉  卡伯特夫人
I'm sorry, Mrs. Cabot,
我们要跟你儿子谈谈
but we need to speak to your son.
你妈妈不知情  对不对
Your mom doesn't know, does she?
不过你知道
But you do.
你知道他的身份
You knew who he was,
知道他是如何毁了你们的生活
and how he ruined your lives.
没错
Yeah.
我都知道
Yeah, I-I knew.
蒂姆  什
Tim, wh--
都是艾德干的  妈
It was, Ed, mom.
他曾经在日湾工作  是他把我们害成这样
He was SunCove. He's the one who bled us dry.
艾德  帮我们的艾德吗
Ed? Our Ed?
你发现真相时一定很气愤
You must have been pretty angry when you found out.
当然  我当然生气
Hell, yeah, I was angry.
他告诉我一切时  我真想杀了他
When he told me, I wanted to kill him.
可我没那么做
But I didn't.
等等
Wait.
他告诉了你
He told you?
没错  就在上周
Yeah. Last week.
他乞求我的原谅
He asked for my forgiveness
说自己想弥补我们
and he said he wanted to make things right.
律师本来要放弃诉讼了
The lawyer was gonna drop the lawsuit,
可艾德说他不能再袖手旁观
but Ed said he couldn't sit by anymore.
他知道能让我们赢下官司的关键证据在哪
He knew where there was evidence that could win our case,
可他需要我帮忙
but he needed my help.
什么样的忙
What kind of help?
我很擅长开锁
I'm good with locks, all right?
他让我跟着服务员溜进那个派对
He needed me to slip in to the party with the waitstaff
然后撬开后面储藏室的们
and jimmy open the storage room door in back.
为什么你之前不告诉我们
And why didn't you tell us this before?
因为我不能再让自己陷入麻烦了
Because I couldn't get in trouble again.
我得在家陪我妈
I need to be here for my mom.
储藏室里都有什么
What was in the storage room?
文件  有好几箱
Files. Boxes of 'em.
艾德蒙德说这些都是原始文件
Edmund said that they were the original,
是日湾公司未经篡改的贷款文件
unaltered loan docs from SunCove.
这就是为了打赢官司他所需要的证据
They were the evidence he needed to set things right.
他过去的某个同事肯定在凯斯商务工作
One of his old partners must be at Case Commerce.
他认出了艾德蒙德
He recognized Edmund,
意识到他是来偷文件的
realized he was going after those files.
这就是为什么他需要直升飞机
And that's why he needed the helicopter.
带着文件他没法从前门出去
He couldn't exactly cart them out the front door.
由于整个楼层都是警察
And with the cops all over the building,
凶手也没办法销毁那些文件
it would've been risky for the killer to destroy them.
说明文件还在原处
Which means they're still there.
跟凶手在一起
Along with our killer.
我想拦下他们  可他们有搜查令
I tried to stop them, but they had a warrant.
这到底是怎么一回事
What the hell is this all about?
我们也正想说同样的话
We were about to ask you the same thing.
告诉你们
I'm telling you,
我从来没见过这些文件
I've never seen those files in my life.
那它们怎么会在
So then what were they doing
你办公室的储藏室  凯斯先生
in your office storage space, Mr. Case?
我完全不知情
I don't have the slightest idea.
我们真的要这么周旋下去
Are we really gonna play this game,
看你否认一些咱们都心知肚明的事情吗
where you deny things that you and I both know are true?
就像上次
Like you telling me
你告诉我们不认识艾德蒙德一样
that you didn't know Edmund?
我们做了背景调查
We ran a background check.
你跟艾德蒙德曾是商业伙伴
You and Edmund were business associates.
你不会否认自己认识他
So why would you claim that you didn't know him
除非你是想隐藏什么
unless you were hiding something,
比如说过去在日湾基金公司工作过的事实
like your involvement with SunCove Funding?
你们俩是不是谈论过如果扭曲规则
Did the two of you talk about how much money you could make
就可以赚大钱
if you could just bend the rules,
做一些造假文件就可以轻而易举
how easy it would be to forge documents
让人们背负起自己根本还不起的债务
to put people into mortgages that they couldn't afford,
然后把他们的房子卖给投资者
and how you could make a quick buck
自己就可以赚一大笔呢
by selling them off to investors?
光凭这些文件你们根本查不到我头上
There's nothing in those files that can implicate me,
也无法证明我跟日湾基金公司
and nothing to tie me to SunCove Funding
或那个男人的死有何关系
or to that man's death.
那个被偷的钟是从哪来的
That clock that was stolen, where did it come from?
不知道  我得问问室内装潢师
I'm not sure. I'll have to ask my decorator.
别麻烦了  我们已经
Don't bother. We already have documents
拿到文件证明它是卡伯特家的东西
that prove it belonged to the Cabots.
卡伯特一家是什么人
Who are the Cabots?
是你曾经谋害过的众多家庭中的某个
One of the families whose house you stole.
他们把那口钟作为贷款抵押品
They put that clock up as collateral against a loan,
还不起贷款时
and when they couldn't make the payments,
日湾就有权扣押那口钟
SunCove Funding kept it,
就是它
and that...
能证明你在日湾工作过
connects you to SunCove.
你那晚见到艾德蒙德时
When you saw Edmund that night,
就意识到他是为了那些文件而来的
you realized that he was going after the files
因为他打算曝光日湾
because he was gonna blow the whistle on SunCove.
你知道艾德蒙德会把你也牵连进去
You knew that Edmund could implicate you,
于是你就杀了他
so you killed him.
不  你错了
No. You're wrong.
检察院会冻结你所有资产
The U.S. Attorneys' office would freeze your assets.
你所有的钱都会被没收
They would seize all of your money.
你会失去一切
You were gonna lose everything.
动机有了  机会也有了
Now that is motive, that is opportunity,
足够让陪审团给你定罪了
and that is enough for any jury to convict you.
我没杀艾德蒙德
I did not kill Edmund.
但是我知道凶手是谁
But I know who did.
她来了
She was here.
她来参加派对了
She stopped by the party.
开什么玩笑  我为什么要杀他
You must be kidding me? Why would I kill him?
因为他无法再这样活下去
Because he couldn't live with himself any longer,
他为自己的行为感到愧疚
with what he had done,
那就意味着他将夺走
which meant that he was gonna take away
离婚后  他留给你的唯一一样东西
the one thing that he left you after the divorce--
富足的生活
Your lifestyle,
那生活是依靠日湾供给的
paid for by Suncove Profits.
他不是找你来道歉的
He didn't come to you to apologize that night, did he?
他来警告你
He came to warn you, because he knew
因为他知道他一旦举报了日湾
that if he blew the whistle on Suncove,
你就失去了一切
you stood to lose everything.
这太荒谬了
This is absurd.
你知道他要去哪  你也知道原因
You knew where he was going and you knew why.
所以你跟踪他来到房顶
So you followed him to the rooftop,
射杀了他
and then you shot him.
我当时在参加慈善晚宴
I was at the benefit.
我们知道你在凯斯商务
We know you were at Case Commerce.
我们有目击证人  你杀了艾德蒙德
We have a witness. You killed Edmund.
当他离开的时候  他说他没想过伤害我
When he left me, he told me, he never wanted to hurt me.
在伤害你之前
That's what people always say
人们都这么说
right before they hurt you.
是的  他留给了我富足的生活
Yes, he left me my lifestyle.
五年之后  他出现在我门口
Five years later, he shows up on my doorstep,
再次对我说他没想过要伤害我
Telling me again how he doesn't want to hurt me.
知道最糟糕的是什么吗
You know what the worst part is?
有那么一刻  看到他站在那
Just for a moment, when he stood there that night,
我好开心
I was happy to see him.
你得佩服这家伙
You got to admire the guy.
放弃了所有去弥补过失
Sacrificed everything to redeem himself.
最后还是被过去夺去了生命真可惜
It's too bad his past caught up with him.
不管怎么说  那些档案寄到检察院去了
Still, those files are on their way to the U.S. Attorneys' office.
卡伯特一家有机会夺回失去的东西了
Now the Cabots have a real shot at getting back what they lost.
还有其他42个家庭
Along with the 42 other families,
都是因为艾德蒙德
All because of Edmund.
说到家被人偷了
Speaking of people having their homes stolen...
又是你婆婆吗  长官
Is that your mother-in-law again, sir?
探长  如果你今天收到消息
Detective, if you happen to receive a report
我家发生了命案
of a homicide tonight at my address,
帮了忙
do me a favor.
-不要理会  -遵命
- Ignore it. - Yes, sir.
卡塞尔  看来你是对的
Well, Castle. Looks like you might have been right.
还真有圣诞老人
Maybe there is a Santa Claus after all.
不管有没有圣诞老人
Whether there's a Santa Claus or not,
那不是我爱圣诞节的原因
that's not why I love christmas.
我小时候
When I was a kid,
不管生活有多糟
no matter how bad things got,
我妈总是能把圣诞节前夜变得很梦幻
my mother always managed to make Christmas Eve magical.
每年她都会放《胡桃夹子》
Every year she would put on "The nutcracker suite."
我就想  在我们既穷又孤独的时候
And I thought, if she can do that in our tiny apartment
她都能让我们的小公寓那么有节日气氛
when money was tight and we were alone,
那给了我希望  一切会好起来
it gave me hope that things could get better.
我喜欢那种感觉  希望的感觉
I love that feeling, that sense of hope.
其实挺奇怪的
It's crazy, you know?
在全年最短最黑的一天
On the shortest, darkest days of the year,
所有人都在庆祝光明
people of all faiths celebrate the light.
再说了  谁会不喜欢礼物
Plus, who doesn't love presents?
圣诞节快乐
Merry christmas.
You, too.
你怎么还没走
What you still doing here?
不是应该回去
Shouldn't you be at home,
给老婆的袜子里塞礼物了吗
stuffing your wife's stocking?
我觉得自己还没准备好  哈维
I don't think I'm ready, Javi.
你是说上床吗
For what, sex?
不是  是之后的事
No, for what sex leads to.
我们把圣诞树立起来那天
We're putting up the tree the other day,
珍妮说
Jenny says to me,
没有孩子感觉不像圣诞节
"It just doesn't feel like Christmas without kids."
她想要孩子
She wants to try.
但是我来到局里
But I come to work,
看着每天的新闻
I watch the news every day...
感觉这世界要崩塌了
It seems like the world's falling apart.
我怎么能把孩子带到这个世上呢
How am I supposed to bring a kid into that?
这世界一直在崩塌
The world's always falling apart, bro,
但正是成家生子
But having kids, making a family,
让世界美好起来
that's what keeps it together.
回家吧
So go home.
开始造人
Make a baby.
你准备好了
You're ready.
是啊
Yeah.
谢了  兄弟
Thanks, bro.
圣诞快乐
Merry Christmas.
Yeah. Merry Christmas.
老妈  格拉格酒太赞了
Mother, the glogg is excellent.
谢谢
And... thank you.
一切都很赞
Everything looks excellent.
跟往常一样
Just like always.
理查德  亲爱的
Oh, Richard, Richard, darling,
没必要这么沮丧
you don't have to look so miserable.
奶奶说得对  爸
Oh-- she's right, dad.
我们知道这传统对你来说有多重要
We know how much this tradition means to you.
所以我们都决定取消我们的计划
So we both decided to cancel our plans.
我们整晚都在
We're here all night,
跟往常一样
Like always.
你们为我这样做  我很爱你们
I love you both so much that you would do that for me.
但关于今晚  我是错的
But I was wrong about tonight.
我要去一个地方
There's someplace I need to be.
-爸  我  -去吧
Dad, I-- - Go.
走吧
Go, go, go.
我
I...
我正要去见你
Uh... I was just coming to see you.
我也是
I was coming to see you.
你的轮班怎么办
What about your shift?
我让卡波斯基替我了
I got Karpowski to cover.
你家的传统怎么办
What about your family tradition?
我在想  是时候换个真传统了
I was just thinking, it's time for a new tradition.
我也是
Me, too.
老天
Oh, for god sakes,
理查德  赶紧请姑娘进来
Richard, invite the girl in.
哦对  你
Right. Would you...
好
Yeah.
真美
It's beautiful.
圣诞快乐
Merry christmas.
我没给你买什么
I didn't get you anything.
什么
What?
卡伯特太太
Mrs. Cabot?
我是埃斯波西托警探
I'm Detective Esposito.
我这有件东西是你的
I have something that I think belongs to you.
我们发现你丈夫把这个作为抵押物
We found out that your husband put that up for collateral
还你们房子的贷款
against the mortgage on your house.
我好久没看到这个了
I haven't seen this for so long.
这在他家传了好几代
It was handed down through his family for generations.
所以艾德蒙德才会拿走
I think that's why Edmund took it.
他想还给你
He wanted you to have it back.
谢谢
Thank you.
等下
Wait.
你进屋坐坐吧  我们刚好在吃晚饭
Why don't you come inside? We're just having dinner.
好啊
Okay.